Guide to the Duke Gardens Foundation records, 1912-2002 and undated
Duke University. University Archives
Duke Gardens Foundation records 1912-2002 and undated
Duke University. University Archives
Duke Gardens Foundation
96.8 linear feet Extent: 28,000 Items
On October 15, 1958 the Duke Gardens Foundation was incorporated with the purpose of "developing thereon agricultural, botanical & horticultural exhibits for the purpose of scientific experiments and of public inspection, instruction, education & enjoyment." Over the period of six years, Doris Duke was personally involved in the physical design of the Indoor Display Gardens, in which various gardens were carefully designed, planned, and developed from the point of view of authenticity. The gardens were opened to the public in 1964, and included 11 unique gardens for visitors to enjoy. Doris Duke continued her involvement with her gardens throughout her life, bringing designers with her to modify them during the summer season when they were closed to tourists. The Duke Gardens Foundation was officially dissolved November 13, 2001 and the gardens closed to the public in 2008. The collection documents the lifecycle of the Duke Gardens Foundation, beginning with the inception of the Duke Gardens Foundation and the design and creation of the various indoor display gardens that comprised Duke Gardens, including the associated purchases of plants and bulbs. The materials follow the daily operations of Duke Gardens, including modifications and general upkeep of the gardens, visitor and tour information, and operations of the Foundation itself. The materials end with the general management of Duke Gardens after Doris Duke's death in 1993 and the final dissolution of the Foundation in 2001. Materials include correspondence, inventories, specifications for various architectural projects at Duke Gardens, invoices and vouchers for repairs and reconstruction to the greenhouses, surveys and reports, financial ledgers, and a multitude of both black and white and color photographs and slides of the different gardens.
RL.01438
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, however there are restrictions on certain materials within the collection. See Series level descriptions for more information.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use. Due to the fragility of the architectural records, The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Digital use copies in this collection have been migrated to a library server and can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access please contact a reference archivist prior to visiting the library.
Provenance
The Duke Gardens Foundation Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a donation from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in June 2009.
Historical Note
A visit to Longwood Gardens in Pennsylvania prompted Doris Duke to find a new purpose for the empty greenhouses that had fallen into disrepair at her Duke Farms estate in Somerville, New Jersey. Originally established by her father James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke, the greenhouses were constructed to grow various fruits and flowers, particularly orchids. In the 1950s, Doris Duke set about modernizing and repairing the structures and on October 15, 1958 incorporated the Duke Gardens Foundation with the purpose of "developing thereon agricultural, botanical & horticultural exhibits for the purpose of scientific experiments and of public inspection, instruction, education & enjoyment." Over the period of six years, Doris Duke was personally involved in the physical design of the Indoor Display Gardens, in which various gardens were carefully designed, planned, and developed from the point of view of authenticity. Although she lacked specific botanical knowledge, she had a clear vision of the spaces and features she wanted to create and designed all but one of the gardens, incorporating her interests in color, design and fragrance. The gardens were opened to the public in 1964, and included 11 unique gardens for visitors to enjoy. Doris Duke continued her involvement with her gardens throughout her life, bringing designers with her to modify them during the summer season when they were closed to tourists. The Duke Gardens Foundation was officially dissolved November 13, 2001 and the gardens closed to the public in 2008.
The Duke Gardens Foundation records (formerly DGF.13) is part of the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation Historical Archives which were donated to the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library by the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. The collection is arranged into five series: Administrative Records, Financial Records, Photographs/Slides, Legal Records, and Architectural Records. It primarily spans the years 1912 to 2002, although a bulk of the materials date from 1958 to 1999. The collection documents the lifecycle of the Duke Gardens Foundation, beginning with the inception of the Duke Gardens Foundation and the design and creation of the various indoor display gardens that comprised Duke Gardens, including the associated purchases of plants and bulbs. The materials follow the daily operations of Duke Gardens, including modifications and general upkeep of the gardens, visitor and tour information, and operations of the Foundation itself. The materials end with the general management of Duke Gardens after Doris Duke's death in 1993 and the final dissolution of the Foundation in 2001. Materials include correspondence (including thank you letters from visitors), inventories, specifications for various architectural projects at Duke Gardens, invoices and vouchers for repairs and reconstruction to the greenhouses, surveys and reports, financial ledgers, and a multitude of both black and white and color photographs and slides of the different gardens. The arrangement of the collection varies with each series.
Subject Headings
Architecture -- Designs and plans; Architectural drawing -- United States -- 20th Century; Botanical gardens; Duke, Doris, 1912-1993; Duke, James Buchanan, 1856-1925; Somerville (N.J.)
Related Material
Duke Family Papers on the Duke Farms Residence, 1859-2004 and undated
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Contents of Collection
- Administrative Records, 1939-2002 and undated
  Topics in this series are widely varied; however they are all related to the daily operations of the Duke Gardens Foundation and the Indoor Display Gardens, including the original agreement between Doris Duke and the Duke Gardens Foundation outlining the purpose of the Foundation. Also included are board meetings and minutes, progress reports, correspondence, notes, and invoices regarding design, set up, and materials for the different display gardens, correspondence and memoranda regarding purchases and donations of plant materials, clippings and brochures related to the opening and success of the gardens, property appraisals, inventories, and other general administrative materials. Boxes 34-54 contain logs of different activities such as registries for garden tours, in and out logs, and schedules for evening tours. Of particular interest are the thank you letters, many addressed to either Doris Duke or to the Tour Guides who gave the garden tours.
  The administrative records also contain architectural records, which were not separated out and included in the Architectural Records series in order to give its associated correspondence context. Additionally, intermixed with the Duke Gardens Foundation Records are Duke Farms records including rental house agreements, repairs to rental houses, and other repairs to buildings on the Duke Farms property.
  This series is arranged chronologically and alphabetically thereunder.
  - Correspondence relating to building and renovation of Garden facilities, including the aviary and French Garden, 1939-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Signage that hung in DGF office. 1950s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence relating to improvements and work performed on the greenhouse. Topics include its heating system and ground beds purchased from Lord & Burnham. 1952–1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Architectural plan and aerial photograph, black and white, of Phipps Conservatory, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificate of Incorporation of Duke Gardens Foundation Inc. and copy of Certification attesting to incorporation. October 15–16, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agreement between Doris Duke and Duke Gardens Foundation for the use of property on Duke Farms. October 27, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Agreement between The Horticultural Society of N.Y. and the Duke Gardens Foundation. October 27, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memorandum discussing Agreement between the DFF, Doris Duke, and the Horticultural Society of N.Y. in the establishment of the interior gardens. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - By-laws of Duke Gardens Foundation, Inc. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Consent to Election of Directors forms of Duke Gardens Foundation, Inc. 1958 (2 sets) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Real estate appraisal of Doris Duke property in Somerville, N.J., including black and white photographs, made by the Shultise Agency, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - N.Y. Horticultural Society membership certificate for David Rimmer, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Parks and Recreation Plan for Somerset County, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Exotic Plants Illustrated, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence and lists regarding the gift of a camellia collection by Countess Bismarck, of Bayville, Long Island, to Duke Gardens, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence regarding promotional materials for Duke Gardens and examples from other public gardens, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letter and notes related to construction at Duke Gardens, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence - Umberto Innocenti, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Minutes and materials of the Horticultural Society of New York related to Duke Gardens Foundation, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Agreement between Doris Duke and Duke Gardens Foundation, Inc. for use of property on estate (1958) and Indenture between Doris Duke and Duke Gardens Foundation, Inc. assigning Foundation the ownership of land for $1.00 (1961). 1958, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence regarding purchases and donations of plant materials, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Copies of executed documents, including Certificate of Incorporation and indentures for land use, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - plant purchasing and fencing, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence regarding a jug handle entrance to Duke Gardens, 1958-1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cashbook and General Ledger, 1958-1962 (1 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cashbook and General Ledger, 1958-1962 (2 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cashbook and General Ledger, 1958-1962 (3 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cashbook and General Ledger, 1958-1962 (4 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cashbook and General Ledger, 1958-1962 (5 of 5) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Papers of the Board of Directors, includes meeting minutes, consents in lieu of meetings, and resignations, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with garden visitors, including thank you notes, payment transmittals, and requests for brochures and reservations, 1958-1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of Board of Directors of Duke Gardens Foundation, Inc., and related materials, including planting schedules, 1958-1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Pontiac station wagon - invoices, 1958-1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from other organizations regarding the set-up of the interior garden and thank you notes. 1958, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Clippings related to opening and success of Duke Gardens, includes brochures, 1958-1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, brochures, and ephemera related to places of interest including Duke Gardens, Newport, R.I., and the Duke Homestead, 1958-1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence regarding visits to and publicity for Duke Gardens, including black and white photographs and news clippings, 1958-1970 and 1997 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - construction, October 27, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Agreement between Duke Gardens Foundation and The Horticultural Society of N.Y., Inc. December 28, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence regarding design of French Garden, including drawing for a "rose chandelier," 1959 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, notes, and invoices regarding design, set up, and materials for Japanese Garden, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Inventory of Orchid Range plants and notes, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with Frederick Peck regarding redesign of English and French Gardens, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Parking lot, includes work quotes, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence - general administration, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence - greenhouse plants and materials, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - administrative, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Compensation Expenses breakdown, 1959-1964 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and notes - plants, maintenance, and training, 1959-1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to the daily operations of Duke Gardens Foundation. 1959–1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, legal, U.S. Treasury Department forms, (IRS), and related materials concerning legal arrangements between Doris Duke and Duke Gardens Foundation, Inc. 1959–1997 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Botanical lists, 1959, 1964, and undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence regarding analysis of Duke Gardens water supply, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Proposal of hourly rates for machinery rented by Duke Gardens, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence between Jerome Eaton and George Lawrence, M.H., regarding gardens and reference materials, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, lists, and photographs, black and white, regarding setup for Chinese Garden, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence of Doris Duke regarding Duke Gardens, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - Van Tubergen, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence - plants, materials, and literature, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence - greenhouse plants and materials, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Solar heating - 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence - plants and materials, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence - in search of materials, plants, and skilled labor, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - H & E - Electric Co., includes estimate, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - plants, fertilizers, Australian House, and Longwood Gardens, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - Japanese garden and plants, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - plants, fence, and work payment, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - plants and heating, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Water analyses, 1960-1964 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Circular advertising Gardens tours as “Illuminated Evening Tours.” circa 1960s (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Indentures transferring ownership of land from Doris Duke to Duke Gardens Foundation, Inc. (1961) and related correspondence, property appraisals, agreement drafts, and other materials, 1960-1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Lease between Doris Duke and Duke Gardens Foundation for the use of the Orchid Range. June 17, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Report, Duke Gardens Foundation, Inc. October 10, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Western Termite Control invoice, November 7, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Indenture, Doris Duke and Duke Gardens Foundation, transferring greenhouse and parking lot. 1961 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Plans and correspondence regarding the construction of a new administration building, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence and clippings related to outdoor lighting at Duke Gardens, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence and survey report concerning the heating system for growing rooms and display greenhouses and the feasibility of solar heating, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence regarding India Garden, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Bulb cellar - boiler room extension, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Maintenance Building #33, includes architectural record, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Reports of business meetings and other administrative papers, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Survey and report of greenhouse heating by Horace M. Patrick, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence - to Doris Duke, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Solar energy - 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Roads, includes paving and jug handles, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Lattice House, includes brochures and material samples, black and white photograph, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Specifications, for Alterations to the Reception Center and the Gardens, Tectonic Associates. 1961–1962 (Removed from Architectural Drawings Collection, C2, January 22, 2004) (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence between Duke Gardens employees and Edwardo Tirella, 1961-1964 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Publicity requests and information, 1961-1967 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Water consumption - electricity, 1961-1967 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence relating to contributions made to the Duke Gardens Foundation from the Doris Duke Foundation. 1961–1962, 1971–1972 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Lease of Orchid Range to Duke Gardens Foundation, Inc. (1961) and Deed of Orchid Range to Foundation (1980). 1961, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Report, Duke Gardens Foundation, Inc. April 16, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Letter from R. N. Eberhardt regarding dead spruce tree, August 30, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence regarding solar water heater, includes invoices, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Greenhouse soil analysis report, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Article - plexiglas, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - administration and maintenance, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Progress and greenhouse reports, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Greenhouse Reports, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence regarding lighting in display houses, includes brochures, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Inventories of tools, 1962, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Planting Schedule for the Duke Gardens for 1964, September 7, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Book, "Blueprint Reading and Sketching," identified as "DG 543," 1963 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Agreements creating pension fund for Duke Gardens employees, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Burns Detective Agency, night security guards, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - New York Botanical Garden Financial Statements, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence - chemicals, lawn, and swans, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Horticulture education, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Work orders, 1963-1969 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Minutes of postponed annual meeting of members of Duke Gardens Foundation, Inc., 29 April 1964 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Rental fee listings - Duke Farms and contract, June 1964 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Deed, Doris Duke to Duke Gardens Foundation, land sold on Duke Farms for $1.00. Signed by DD. August 28, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Sungas Distributors - rates, November 6, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Certificate, 1 share of Membership Common Stock. 1964 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Appraisal, 2.204 acres and Houses Nos. 29 and 30 by the Shultise Agency, Inc., 1964 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Magazine, “Under Glass: The Home Greenhouse Gardener’s Magazine” with article on Duke Gardens. 1964 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Newsletter, Horticultural Society of N.Y. with Information on DGF. 1964 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence relating to public relations contract with Allan, Foster, Ingersoll & Weber, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - 1965 planting schedule, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - International 240 tractor - service invoice, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Rutgers - soil report, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Planting schedule, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Lord & Burnham - correspondence, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence relating to public relations contract with Allan, Foster, Ingersoll & Weber, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Working papers for map to Duke Gardens, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Greenhouse Reports, 1964-1965 (1 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Greenhouse Reports, 1964-1965 (2 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Volkswagen bus, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - International bus - service invoices, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Greenhouse materials, reports of employee hours worked, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence and related materials regarding boilers in greenhouses, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence with public relations firm of Allan, Ingersoll & Weber, released in 1965, and requests for permission to photograph and publish material on gardens, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence - administrative, 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, lists, and receipts related to general administration of gardens, 1964-1966 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Descriptions of gardens, 1964-1965, 1967-1968 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Publicity materials, including magazine and newspaper clippings, black and white photos, and related correspondence, 1964-1968 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Admissions - weekly and monthly, 1964-1978 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Vehicle #44 - 1964 International bus, 1964-1985 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Bills of sale relating to the purchase and sale of automobiles for DGF and other car-related materials. 1964–1994 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence relating to David Rimmer’s position on the Board of the Duke Gardens Foundation. All materials photocopied from originals still with D. Rimmer. 1964, 1992–1995 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Comet station wagon - invoice, January 21, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Thank you letter for a tour of the Duke Gardens, March 7, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Director's Meeting notes - Doris Duke, September 2, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Proposal for Duke Farms sewerage system by Richard H. Schindlear, includes architectural record, 10 December 1965 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Waiver of Notices of Special Meeting of The Board of Directors of Duke Gardens Foundation, Inc. 1965 (2 sets) (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Planting schedule, interior gardens. 1965 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Chevrolet pick-up truck - service invoices, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - 1963 Thunderbird invoice, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Planting schedules and notes, 1965-1967 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence regarding requests for publicity, 1965-1967 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Meeting reports, memoranda to Miss Duke, and other papers of the Duke Gardens Management Committee, 1965-1967 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Reports to Miss Duke, 1965-1970 (1 of 2) (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Reports to Miss Duke, 1965-1970 (2 of 2) (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Maintenance reports, 1965-1970 (1 of 2) (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Maintenance reports, 1965-1970 (2 of 2) (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Plants which Miss Duke was interested in obtaining for the Duke Gardens. 1965, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Weathermatic Irrigation System plan submitted to Robert Dingwall, Supervisor, September 7, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Duke Gardens Foundation ledger book, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Photographic prints and other materials, black and white, relating to a photo shoot in Duke Gardens for a ladies sleep and loungewear collection, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 8)